July 4th 1918
On this day in Moscow, the 5th All-Russian Congress of the Soviets
of Worker, Peasant, Red Army and Cossack deputies was starting.
Petrozavodsk.
To the chrezvoenkom* Natsarenus.
* emergency military comissioner
I'm passing your telegram
to the Narkomprod*.
* The People's Commissariat of Food Supply
Food supply is at its worst.
The bread expected from Tsaritsyn...
- Vladimir Ilyich, excuse me, you
have to be there an hour earlier.
- ...is still not here.
There's none being passed out today.
Not in Peter*,
* St Petersburg
not in Moscow.
In the upcoming days
we can't be of any help.
We are bled
absolutely dry.
Are you here for me?
For the chair committee.
They're on the second floor.
- And Yakov Mikhaylovich?..
- I think he's around.
- Thank you.
You have to
mobilize
all the best
to send troops to the
Czechoslovakian front.
Without victory over Czechoslovakians
there will be no bread.
Predsovnarkoma* Ulyanov-Lenin.
* Chairman of the Council of People's Commissars
Excuse me. Greetings.
We had an emergency meeting
of the Central Committee.
Take you seats, comrades.
And we were already ready to plan
the Congress' proceedings without you.
And now on to the construction
of the Congress' presidium.
Same principle.
One presidium member for every fifty delegates.
No objections?
Consequently,
the Bolsheviks have fourteen seats,
the Left SRs have six,
the Maximalists...
- There's only thirty of us.
- And six Internationalist Democrats.
- Two more could still turn up.
- Or three.
- Alright.
Your parties' representatives
will get seats on the mandates commission.
Therefore...
- Our party delegates for the Congress presidium shall be Karelin,
Golubovsky,
Kolegayev,
Spiridonova,
Kamkov
and Cherepanov.
Cherepanov... Good.
The agenda seems to be as follows:
Sovnarkom*'s and VTsIK**'s reports,
*Council of People's Commissars
**All-Russian Central Executive Committee
the question of food security,
the military question,
the ratification of the constitution.
We would think it necessary to
add local reports to the agenda.
I'm afraid it would significantly drag out our work.
But I fully agree with the Maximalists.
We do as well.
We do need local reports.
Let's hear them out on
factional meetings then.
Any objections?
Any suggestions or additions?
Our party suggests emphasizing
the Brest Peace question.
I don't think it expedient. The Brest Peace
question will be brought up in reports and debates.
Certainly in the debates.
I think we can agree with that.
So be it.
About the makeup of the mandates commission...
- Yes?
- On second thought, we will fight you
on the Congress itself over this question.
Perhaps, considering the stressful times...
Afraid of the criticisms?
I'm afraid of bloody quarrels
between two Soviet parties.
- Assuming though that both parties
are Soviet.
- I agree with you on that.
- If only we'd always find common ground as easily.
- It's not for the Bolsheviks, of any people, to accuse us of recalcitrance.
And the last.
Alexandrov from Ukraine has come over.
We would ask to let him speak at the opening.
- Alright.
The next question.
Please proceed.
- Comrades...
For two months already
the German imperialists, after
signing the Brest Peace,
came to Ukraine and toppled the Soviet rule there.
(speaking: A. P. Alexandrov, representative of the
underground Peasant Congress of Ukraine)
By now the bourgeoisie has regained the power
that was taken from them by our October revolution.
The Germans are shooting the members of the land committees.
They are shooting rebel peasants.
They aren't sparing the elderly,
women or children.
There isn't a corner of Ukraine not plastered
with notices of the new executions.
Thousands have been shot dead.
Thousands are waiting for their turn.
This is what the Brest Peace has given to Ukraine.
Comrades!
But the Ukrainian toiling peasantry
and the Ukrainian proletariat are skilled in fighting!
And they are fighting their enemies!
Right now in Ukraine
in every governorate
rebellions are flaring up.
The peasantry is rising up.
(note： Alexandrov is knowingly riling tension. Who is he? A left SR or their associate? Lenin.)
They are organizing troops.
And where possible,
(note： Alexandrov is knowingly riling tension. Who is he? A left SR or their associate? Lenin.)
they are driving Germans back.
The Ukrainians are fighting,
but, comrades,
they are outmatched.
Ukraine is bleeding out.
Speaking for our Congress,
we're addressing the All-Russian Congress
with a request for help.
Help us!
Comrade Lenin, support the Ukrainians!
Down with the Brest Peace!
I have no doubts
that in large part the ovation and applause
earned by the speaker
are addressing not his words,
but fully and explicitly
the fighting Ukrainian
workers and peasants.
Hail Ukraine!
Hail the Ukrainian workers and peasants!
On the matter of
the Brest Treaty,
I think that this question will be resolved
by the will of this Congress,
and not by some or other,
even the most sincere exclamations.
Announcing a twenty minute recess.
Understand, we are
powerless about this!
But what about the power
of the revolutionary ideas?
Does it count for nothing for you?
What war are you talking about,
when the people have nothing to eat?
There is no bread!
And where would the bread come from?
Germany is an adventure!
- And you're betting on a break! It's treason!
What about the Black Sea Fleet? Who sank it?
So what, should it have been surrendered to the Germans?
- We should have fought for it!
- With what?
- With your hands!
- Go fawn over von Mirbach, that provocateur and murderer!
- Traitors of the revolution!
- And you are talking about revolution?
- Where were you and your party in October?
- We were on the barricades!
- We haven't seen you there!
- Don't slander us, you liar!
- Comrades, stop, have you gone mad?
- I fully agree with comrade Lenin!
Mister Sverdlov.
Can I distract you for a minute?
Calling to end the Brest Treaty,
the Left SRs are claiming that
it is them who truly represent the public
opinion of the Russian people.
What people?
Workers, peasants?
The left SRs are affected by the public
bourgeois opinion, that much is true.
- I understand.
- The bourgeois public opinion.
They are interested in the public opinion of the kulaks,
who are dissatisfied with the Soviet
power not because of the Brest Treaty,
but because of our food security policy.
This is true as well.
But neither the said kulaks nor the peasants,
not to mention the working
class, nobody wants war.
and this is the actual truth.
Yes. One more question, Mr Sverdlov.
What do you think about Mariya Spiridonova?
As a leader of the Left SR party
and as a person.
- Excuse me.
Comrade Sergeyev!
This is your department.
Look into it.
As a party leader, I think
she can be fully characterized
by the same qualities
I proscribed to the whole party in general.
And as a person, unfortunately,
in political struggle one does not
think about that too often.
But she is certainly a courageous and
sincere person.
You must have known she shot at a tsar's general in 1906.
- 1906?
- Who was known by his cruelty.
Gendarmes...
Comrade Sablin!
I need you. One minute.
Gendarmes had outraged her abominably,
then prison, katorga,
our Rossiyan katorga,
she only had been freed by the February revolution.
Don't you think that
with a biography like that
it's her that could become
the nation's true leader?
I don't. Revolutionary biographies do not prevent
mistakes and political misconceptions.
Unfortunately, it's not some eternal capital.
Again the only supplies coming
will be oil cake and sunflower seeds.
And those two train cars won't solve anything anyway.
Vladimir Ilyich, the tensions in the theater are red hot.
Latsis and Kamkov have nearly come to blows in the foyer just
now, every minute now a real fight could happen.
Talk to Spiridonova, let
her placate her friends,
and I will ask Yakov Mikhaylovich
to cool down our faction.
Vladimir Ilyich.
A telegram from Kaluga.
I will pass your request
to Yakov Mikhaylovich.
- Yes, yes.
Please learn how many mandates do we
have, and how many the Bolshevik faction does.
- Marya Alexandrovna!
This can't go on, I ask
you to talk with your people.
What happened?
There is a fight coming up.
What does that have to do with me?
It depends on your actions, not on me.
So there's how it is,
they are going to shower us with
curses and we must stay silent.
Why silent?
There are many means of polemics
somewhere in between silence and fighting.
- Stop all talking!
Attention!
Everybody look this way!
Attention.
Shooting.
One. Two.
Three.
Four.
(sign: ...of the Soviets of the Worker, Peasant, Red Army and Cossack deputies)
Five.
Six.
(sign: ...of the Soviets of the Worker, Peasant, Red Army and Cossack deputies)
Seven.
Eight.
(sign: ...of the Soviets of the Worker, Peasant, Red Army and Cossack deputies)
Nine.
Ten.
One more time. Nobody walk off.
Comrades, nobody walk off, one more time!
I don't recognize Lenin.
The Lenin of the October,
the fighting revolutionary leader of the masses,
who had one ideal,
one goal - the revolution!
And who is now calculating and accounting.
Who wants to deal amicably with the German imperialism
while hoping both
to keep his innocence
and acquire his capital.
I'm saying this with the greatest sorrow and grief.
I'm still closely tied to the Bolsheviks
after fighting side by side
on the same barricades
and willing to follow through our glorious way of struggle side by side.
(speaking: M. A. Spiridonova, the leader of the Socialist Revolutionary (Left) party)
Comrades.
Comrades Bolsheviks.
I'm asking you,
do you understand what's happening?
We are retreating after arduous battle
with a wounded comrade in our hands.
Will we really give him up to our enemy
to save our own lives
at the cost of his demise?
That is what
the Bolshevik government is doing now.
It is leaving for the hands of torturers
our freedom,
our ideals,
the revolution!
And demands from us to be silent witnesses
of the demise of our comrades!
Raiders have broken into our home!
They are killing our brothers,
raping our sisters,
and we are sitting in the room next door
afraid of moving so we don't get our share!
If this is the position of
the Soviet government,
then we, the party of left
revolutionary socialists,
are not going to go along
with this government.
Our revolution is a hearth,
and its sparks are
scattering everywhere
to inflame the great fire
of the world revolution!
Peoples of the world
are watching us with hope
and we must declare to the face
of our beaten brothers, Ukrainians,
to the face of our
downtrodden Finnish brothers,
to the face of the
toilers of the whole world
who are expecting of us to be fighting,
not drop to our knees!
Down
with the Brest Peace!
Down with all the talking of Brest!
Down with the opportunists!
Hail
to the fighting Ukraine!
Comrade Lenin, you have the floor.
Comrades,
allow me
despite the fact that the
previous orator's speech
was in places greatly agitated
to present you with my report,
speaking for the Council
of the People Commissars
as per usual,
touching upon the main principal questions
as they deserve.
I understand the anxiety,
the feelings that belied Mariya
Alexandrovna Spiridonova's speech.
She is a person whose
sincerity and devotion to her idea
can't be cast doubt on by any of us.
But in politics
one should have not only a flaming heart,
but also a sober,
cool head.
Or there will always be the danger
of getting fooled.
Comrades.
You know that since
the time of the last Congress
the main factor
defining our position,
having changed our tactics
and defined our politics
has been the Brest Peace.
Allow me to elaborate on this.
A war of many years
has left Russia's body in wounds.
Landlords, tsars and capitalists
left us with the inheritance
of greatest disrepair.
Our people today is like
a man beaten to within an inch of his life.
Our young republic,
having not yet been
able to stand on its feet,
must be involved in a
desperate, uneven fight.
Surrounded by a ring of
fire of counterrevolution,
mutiny,
blockade,
White Czechoslovakians' rebellion,
English and French in the north,
General Krasnov on the Don.
The country lacks bread.
In practice, we don't have any.
Add to this the epidemics of typhus,
cholera,
scurvy!
And finally, the eight German divisions
standing behind our backs
on the Orsha-Mogilev line,
ready to strike at us at a moment's notice
with all their power.
And in these conditions
there are still people
suggesting that we start a war with Germany
and break this
yes, an unjust one
and yes, a shameful one!
but vital to us
peace.
Claiming that our revolution
has got one dilemma only -
that it's either peace,
and consequently betrayal,
or a holy and noble revolutionary war,
our opponents are deliberately lying.
Because our dilemma is
a completely different one.
It's either a brutal,
demeaning peace,
or the demise of Soviet rule.
The most important question,
the final measure of every
revolution is one thing:
what has it given to the people?
We've had inscribed on our October banners
two words:
peace
and land.
But if we follow the left SRs today
then the land rights
for the peasants
whose interests are allegedly
represented by the left SRs
will turn for them into the rights
for the plots of their graves.
The Left SRs are claiming that they
are ready to go even with this.
Yes, we are retreating now.
It is a bitter,
demeaning truth.
But we don't have any other choice
because a war today,
and no one should have
any illusions about this,
means death for the Soviet rule.
The fate of the world revolution
is precious to us Bolsheviks no
less that they are to the left SRs.
Of course the people can be
cast into the fire of world revolution,
the fire that comrade
Spiridonova was talking about here.
But humans aren't firewood.
We have
a living child.
It is our
paid with blood
republic of the Soviets.
Peoples of the world are
trusting us with keeping
this child alive.
And we don't have, right now,
any holier purpose.
By the majority of the votes, the Congress accepts the resolution
of the Bolshevik faction endorsing the actions of the Sovnarkom.
July 6th 1918
The Central Committee of the Left Socialist Revolutionary
party has gathered for an emergency meeting.
To this end the CC of the party
considers permittable and worthwhile
to organize a series of acts of terror
upon the most notable representatives of the German imperialism.
At the same time
the party CC is ruling...
Comrades, I don't understand why
we are listening to all this!
We have very little time,
we all perfectly remember the CC's verdict.
You are absolutely wrong.
We're making a decision
that could decide entirely
the fate of our revolution.
We must analyze all this
very seriosly, without any hurry.
We need everyone to
decide on this themselves.
Mariya Alexandrovna is right, please continue Proshyan.
We are seeing our actions as a struggle against
the policy of the Council of People's Commissars
And not in any way
a struggle against the Bolsheviks.
However,
as the Bolsheviks might
perform acts of aggression
against our party,
the Central Committee is ruling
to commit in that case to armed defense
of the taken positions.
Armed defense.
Comrades, please speak.
I think the decision is clear.
I think so too.
Lenin is right on one point.
The situation in the contry
is indeed very difficult.
I'm afraid in these conditions our
proclamation might be taken the wrong way.
I don't understand,
what are you suggesting?
To agree with a betrayal?
What are you suggesting?
I am suggesting
to take another go at
influencing the Congress.
I am certain that
many of the delegates
are in truth wavering.
Let's try to turn the Congress
around one more time.
I...
I believe I agree with Kolegayev.
Me too.
Let us try.
Comrade Cherepanov,
report on our chances in the Congress.
So far
our every attempt to influence the
Bolsheviks in a democratic fashion failed.
The polling has shown
that tomorrow
in the voting session
we can only count on
400 votes,
while the Bolsheviks have 750 votes.
I don't pretend to know
what's on their minds,
but I think they will be voting
for their party's resolution.
Undoubtedly.
Any more questions?
Concluding.
Having ran out of possibilities
and not willing to allow the
fate of the world revolution
to be a plaything of the
whims of Russian democracy,
we are returning to our
decision made on June 24th.
There is no other way.
Please vote.
Unanimous.
Invite Blumkin.
Vyacheslav Nikolayevich,
is everything ready?
Oreshkin's militia
and the mounted VChK* troops are ready.
*All-Russian Extraordinary Commission
Do you mean Popov's troop?
Yes, Popov's troop, also Pingvinsky's
and the Pervomartovsky regiment.
You think this will suffice?
The people will support us.
The people are tired of war.
They will, should we be winning.
We are also counting on
the Latvian infantry regiment.
We should give extra
attention to the Latvian division.
Yes, very true.
We must send some
dependable comrades there.
We sent three men there.
Go yourself.
We must explain to the Latvian soldiers
that today the liberation of their homeland, Latvia,
depends only on themselves.
Go immediately.
The decision is made.
The party is sending you on this mission.
The Central Committee of the Socialist Revolutionary party (left)
The chief of the Secret Department of VChK, Left SR Yakov Blumkin.
Malaya Lubyanka, 13. The All-Russian Extraordinary Commission for
Combating Counter-Revolution, Sabotage and Profiteering (VChK).
Yes, yes.
Lyusen'ka, is Alexandrovich in his office?
- He is.
- Anything for me?
I don't think so. Here, some papers.
There will be, certainly.
Give me two blank Commission forms, please.
It's not for me.
Yes.
Hello.
IDENTIFICATION.  The All-Russian Extraordinary Commission assigns its member Yakov Blumkin and
the Executive Tribunal representative Nikolay Andreyev to parlay with the German Ambassador...
Are you ready?
Sign it.
Prepare.
- Are the papers in order?
- Mmhm.
Comrade Sergeyev?
Alexandrovich here.
Prepare a car.
Well, godspeed.
I'll walk with you.
- Greetings, Felix Edmundovich.
- Good afternoon.
I was just meaning to come by your office.
I'll catch up.
Yenukidze called again.
Here's his letter.
- Let's meet in an hour and think how we can help.
- Alright.
- And Vyacheslav Nikolayevich?
- Yes?
- Please restrain Kochetov.
His men were shooting through the whole city again.
- They're learning.
- Let them learn somewhere else,
they are scaring the entire Moscow.
A mansion in the Denezhny alley.
The German embassy.
I need to meet someone from the embassy.
No one is in right now.
They're dining.
You can wait inside.
"We had to wait about 15 to 20 minutes".
(from the testimony of Yakov Blumkin)
What do you want, sirs?
We are representatives of the
All-Russian Extraordinary Commission.
Here's our papers.
We need to meet with Mr ambassador.
Ein moment, bitte.
Sirs, Mr Rietzler.
- Are you from Mr Dzerzhinsky?
- Yes.
Mr advisor is listening.
I am the chief of the Secret
Department of the VChK.
Andreyev, representative
of the Revolutionary Tribunal.
We were assigned to discuss a
personal matter with Mr ambassador.
Mr advisor is permitted by Mr
ambassador to speak on any matter.
It concerns the nephew of Mr ambassador,
count Robert Mirbach,
arrested by the VChK
on suspicion of espionage.
Our instructions only permit us to
dicuss it with Mr ambassador in person.
Mr advisor shall inform Mr ambassador.
Please.
Sit, please.
Greetings, sirs.
Please sit.
- Obliged.
- How can I help you?
Mr ambassador, the matter
concerns your family member.
Count Robert Mirbach, your nephew.
I am very sorry, but among my relations
there is no man bearing that name.
Possibly this is some misunderstanding.
The arrested insists he is a descendant
of the Hungarian line of your family.
Count Robert Mirbach is being
accused of espionage for Germany.
You can peruse the papers.
Please sit, sirs.
Nein.
This is a very serious matter, the
tribunal will be assembled in a few days.
I believe we can offer an answer to this
through Mr people's commissar Chicherin.
Well sirs, this is
everything we can do now.
Perhaps Mr ambassador is
interested in the extent of the actions
to be taken concerning the
case of count Robert Mirbach?
"Both myself and Dr Rietzler dropped to the floor on instinct".
(from the testimony of Lt Mueller)
14:47
At the Congress, a recess
was announced at 15:00.
The Kremlin. 15:25
...they want a first
class train car...
..and he got sour.
- Something urgent?
- A telegram.
Put it on my desk,
I'll be back soon.
- Good afternoon!
- Greetings.
Please make sure of it.
I will.
You sure you don't want to come in?
- I can't.
Alright, done.
Vladimir Ilyich.
Mirbach has been assassinated.
A bomb went off at
the German embassy.
Chicherin called.
The killers are on the run.
We know nothing else.
Monarchists, White Guard?
Unclear for now.
We're being dragged into
the war by any means possible.
Vladimir Dmitriyevich.
Find Sverdlov immediately.
Inform all the people's
commissars and CC members.
And go to the embassy,
see what's happening there.
And call Sklyansky.
- Good, right.
I need Dzerzhinsky.
Felix Edmundovich.
Do you know Mirbach has
just been killed with a bomb?
I'm asking you to
investigate this immediately.
Immediately!
Call me, I'm at my office.
Comrade Gorbunov, come with me.
Call for Chicherin.
Mirbach's been assassinated.
Write down the telephonogram.
Yelena Sergeyevna.
Come by please.
To all RKP* district committees.
* Workers and Peasants Party
To all district sovdeps*.
* Soviets of Deputies
To all Red Army command staff.
Today around three o'clock afternoon...
With a bomb...
One minute.
Mirbach was assassinated
at the German embassy.
Listening.
Nothing's clear yet.
Alright.
It was certainly done by either monarchists
or those provocateurs...
- Chicherin is coming.
- ...who want to drag Russia into a war...
...in the interests of the
Anglo-French imperialists...
Can't keep up.
Sorry.
...in the interests of the
Anglo-French imperialists...
...after having
Czechoslovakians bribed.
After having
Yes? Alright.
Some incident...
Mobilize every asset,
call in everyone immediately
to apprehend the perpetrators.
Well, can't complain about
monotonous life so far.
True. Give this to
Churikov, I've signed it.
Stop every car.
And detain them until triple checked.
Triple checked.
The Sovnarkom's Chariman
Ulyanov-Lenin.
Send urgenty.
- Vladimir Ilyich, I'm going.
Go, Vladimir Dmitriyevich, do everything to protect the
Germans from any further possible endangerment.
Listening.
It's Dzerzhinsky.
What do you mean?
By certain appearances,
this was a Left SR action.
What papers?
They presented some
kind of an official mandate.
Well, it's getting worse.
Who was it exactly?
On their own or with the CC in the know?
This is extremely important.
Clarify.
Alright.
I'm waiting.
Even if the CC didn't know,
it would be a result of the hysteria
they promoted at the Congress.
Madness.
Witness another monstrous swaying* of the petit-bourgeois...
*wordplay, Lenin's using an incorrect kolebnutie in reference to the German Kleinburger
That's what Engels said on this:
the frenzied petit-bourgeouis.
Der rabiat gewordene Kleinburger.
Invite Gorbunov, please.
Kleinburger...
Georgiy Vasilyevich*.
* Chicherin
We must influence the upcoming German
report to Berlin in any way possible.
There is more than enough
cause for military intervention.
Especially considering the killers had
a Soviet state mandate on their hands.
Meaning?
They presented some official papers.
Deft!
For the Germans that means we are
directly involved in the assassination.
We must send an
urgent telegram to Berlin.
Let Ioffe offer apologies and condolences
to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs.
We must do everything possible to prevent
the Germans from using this adventure.
They will should they want it. Their
troops are stationed too close to Moscow.
I have left a letter here... Vladimir Ilyich, have you seen it?
- No, no... I haven't.
Listening.
No, the meeting must begin as scheduled。
- Yes, listening.
- Yes, at six exactly.
No. All car passes are now void.
- Listening.
- The only valid signatures are mine and Lenin's.
- One minute. Well?
- We must go to the embassy to express our condolences.
Go then, Georgiy Vasilyevich.
What can we do.
No, Vladimir Ilyich.
If someone should go,
it must be you.
Also Yakov Mikhaylovich and me.
On this question, call Shibayev.
What do they say in situations like this?
Vladimir Ilyich, the VChK
subordinate Blumkin did the shooting.
Do the Germans know this?
He presented these papers.
Your signature is on them.
- The signatues, mine and Ksenofontov's, are forged.
And VChK's seal on
this, is it forged as well?
Felix Edmundovich, Trepalov called.
Blumkin's with the Popov's detachment.
Popov is refusing to give him up.
Does he know that this is an
order of the VChK's chairman?
Trepalov says he has
almost been arrested himself.
- I'm going there.
- Absolutely not! This will only jeopardize...
- Nonsense. If Felix goes, everything will be fine.
- I don't know. I think Vladimir Dmitriyevich
is right. Better to send in some troops.
Still, I'm accountable for the VchK
before the party, Vladimir Ilyich.
Alright, go.
The address of the Soviet government shall be recited by the Chairman
of the Council of People's Commissars, Vladimir Ulyanov-Lenin.
Mr advisor has said that he will tell...
We understand perfectly.
Well. Next time, the ones who do the
shooting should be the ones to go apologize.
To the Kremlin.
Vikula Morozov's mansion. VChK mounted unit (Popov's detachment). 16:50
banner: Hail World Revolution
- Greetings, comrade Dzerzhinsky!
- Greetings, Felix Edmundovich.
- Greetings.
- What's the celebration is about?
- Mirbach has been killed.
- So what?
- You understand, it's serious business.
Hello, Lyalin, where is Popov?
At the headquarters, should I call for him?
Don't.
Greetings. Call Popov to me.
VChK command office.
This is Dzerzhinsky. Call
Alexandrovich, please.
When he turns up, tell
him to call me immediately.
I'm at Popov's.
- Greetings, Felix Edmundovich...
- Where's Blumkin?
- I don't know, Felix Edmundovich.
He's been here, comrade
Belenky here has spoken to him.
He was ill, something wrong with his leg.
- And?
- He took a cab and went for a hospital.
- Has anyone seen him going?
- I have.
- When was it?
- At three or maybe four.
- Who was on guard duty at that time?
- Tkachenko and Shpunker.
- Call for them.
- Their shift has ended,
they went off somewhere.
Give me your word of a revolutionary
that you don't know where Blumkin is.
I'm giving you my word, Felix Edmundovich,
that I indeed don't know if he's here.
Before lying, Popov,
you should learn to lie.
Give up your weapon and follow me.
Have you been here long?
Don't understand.
Those are Finns, Felix Edmundovich,
they don't understand Russian that well.
Have they seen any strangers here?
Felix Edmundovich,
they're saying they've seen
a person not belonging to the detachment.
Tall, dark hair,
they were helping him walk.
Thank you comrades.
- What should we do?
- Who the hell knows.
Wait for me here.
So?
He's arrested Popov,
and is looking for Blumkin.
We should just tell him the truth.
- He's a revolutionary, he'll understand us.
- What does it matter if he knows now or in an hour at the Congress?
You are all mad. He will
arrest us at the spot.
Dzerzhinsky will not dare, he will be obliged
to bring the question before the Congress.
You don't know Dzerzhinsky.
He'll arrest everybody, and immediately.
Yes, and unfortunately he will
have every legal right to do so.
Any of us would do the same in his place.
Well.
In this case we will have
to arrest Dzerzhinsky.
We don't have any other choice.
Yes, unfortunately it's unavoidable.
Then the sooner we do it the better.
I agree.
There's no one in there.
Who's got the key?
- The door is sealed, Felix Edmundovich.
- Break it down.
- I give you my word there's...
- Break it down!
"At this time I was in the detachment's hospital across the street".
(from the Yakov Blumkin's testimony)
You're searching in vain.
Blumkin killed Mirbach
by decree of our party's CC,
and we will not give him up.
On behalf of the All-Russian Extraordinary Commission,
I place you under arrest.
Follow me to my car.
Alright, we will comply.
But we must inform the Cenrtal
Committee of our party of the arrest.
I can't let you in, Felix Edmundovich.
What's happening in this unit?
You've gone insane, all of you!
Felix Edmundovich.
On behalf of the Central Committee
of our party, I place you under arrest.
And demand you
turn in your weapons.
Give up your weapons, Felix Edmundovich.
Well then, comrades.
Will you really allow some mister
to disarm the VChK chairman on your watch?
Do you not understand that this is a
declaration of war on the Soviet rule?
Comrades!
- I demand you help me to arrest this gang of traitors...
- Stop your agitation!
It's a done deal.
The Brest Peace has been breached.
The war on Germany is unavoidable now!
The robbery you were
assisting has come to its end!
The Brest Peace has been
approved by the Soviets Congress.
And attempting to violate it is treason!
The Brest Peace is a
capitulation of our entire project!
This is betrayal of the
revolutionary cause.
It's your own words, comrade Dzerzhinsky!
- We all remember this very well.
- It was a mistake we paid dearly for!
- And which you
are still committed to making,
not seeing where it will lead!
- To the holy revolutionary war!
- To the White Guard* rule, and betrayal!
- And surrendering to the imperialists...
* royalist restoration forces
Ukraine,
Estland*,
* Northern Estonia
Lithuania,
surrendering millions of
our brothers to be massacred,
is this not betrayal?
Disarm him.
It's alright, Felix Edmundovich.
You had your October.
We'll have our July.
- Your entire mutiny
will be crushed within a day.
We will keep you as a hostage
to ensure our comrades'
safety at the Congress.
Take away the arrested.
Let's go, comrades.
So you are going?
The Congress should
hear it from us in person.
Mariya Aleksandrovna.
The lads are worried.
After all it's Dzerzhinsky.
Someone should
explain it all to them.
Alright.
I'll speak to them.
Fyodor!
Get your people.
Send out a guard dispatch, prepare the
armored cars. Everyone else, to the meeting.
- Can't do with the armor. We're out of fuel.
Well, find some.
The Kremlin.
17:10
What's with Berlin?
Silent.
Go ahead.
I've read it, I agree completely.
- So how did it go, Vladimir Ilyich?
- Nothing good so far. We have to go to the Congress.
Is the letter ready for a signature? Let me have it.
Please type a few words, I will dictate.
To Omsk.
To predsovdepa* Turchansky.
* Chairman of the Soviet of Deputies
This is another urgent one.
Has Dzerzhinsky called?
Let's go.
You know, I'm signing this.
Calling Turov.
No, Sverdlov.
Comrade Turov?
We're ready to go.
This all will wait, let's
go comrades, let's go.
We must start the meeting on time.
Vladimir Ilyich!
Someone's asking
for you on a direct line.
Berlin?
Yaroslavl.
Yaroslavl has been taken by the Union for
the Defense of the Motherland and Freedom
led by Savinkov. Comrade Nakhimson has been
shot, all members of the Soviet massacred,
109 of local party administration staff drowned
in the Volga. Requesting military assistance.
Bastards.
What bastards.
Call the narkomvoen*!
* People's Commissar of Military Affairs
I'm going to the Congress now.
Go, Yakov Mikhaylovich.
The narkomvoen is on the line.
Call me at the break.
Greetings.
What has been done to
quell the Yaroslavl mutiny?
When?
Semyonov's reporting the details.
The entire Soviet
has been massacred.
Nakhimson's shot.
109 people have been drowned in the Volga.
I don't want to assume your
staff will be slow to respond,
but I'm asking you to oversee
this personally however possible.
Pull together all forces.
Everything you can and can not.
Give me hourly reports
considering this matter.
We went to the embassy, apologized.
Berlin is keeping silent so far.
- The ways and the agenda of our party are direct and clear!
Popov's detachment
17:20
Through complete denial of any concessions,
through class struggle against landlords
and capitalists,
through rebellion and revolutionary
war against the world bourgeoisie
to the full victory over war,
exploitation,
to the socialist conquest
of the whole world.
We don't want our
brothers' blood to be spilled.
We are calling upon our
Bolshevik brothers to come with us
along the path of the socialist revolution!
We are heading to the Congress
to pronounce before all the toilers,
and to the face of the world imperialism,
our position.
We believe that the Congress delegates
will understand and support us as one!
Hail Soviet rule!
Deadly and merciless war
to the world imperialism!
Ura, comrades!
- Ura!
Moscow was still unaware.
Stop!
What happened, comrade?
Whose car is this?
I am a Congress delegate.
Here.
Here is my mandate.
What happened?
Well listen here, comrade delegate,
get out of the car quick
and move it fast, you understand?
Don't you understand Russian?
Kuzmenko, explain to the comrade.
Comrades, comrades, this is some sort of a misunderstanding.
I am a Congress delegate, you understand?
You've been told to get out,
so get out.
Comrades, this is some sort of misunderstanding.
I will be filing a complaint...
- Listen, bro.
Got a lot of gas?
There is some.
- It's being requisited for the Left SR party. Got it?
Comrades, this is some sort of misunderstanding. Comrades!
I am the delegate of the Kovrov soviet.
My surname is Abelman. I am a Congress delegate, understand?
They are waiting for me. Check my papers and please...
The Kremlin. 17:50
What?
Who reported this?
Khrustalyov, a VChK man.
He went with Dzerzhinsky to the Apropos hotel.
He was able to get out of there.
Immediately contact the Left SRs central committee and learn if they know about this.
Dzerzhinsky has been arrested by the Left SRs central committee.
Everyone was there.
Proshyan, and Spiridonova, and Kolegayev.
They moved their residence to Popov's headquarters.
Well.
Open rebellion.
Mutiny.
Attempt at a palace coup.
Call Podvoysky and Muralov and tell them they are
appointed operational leaders
for counter-insurgency.
For Felix's life the rebels will answer with their heads.
Let them know this.
While Dzerzhinsky is absent the acting VchK head will be Latsis.
About the Left SR faction...
With the arrest of a member of the government
they outlawed themselves.
At the congress, the Left SR faction
is to be arrested.
Tell Sverdlov.
Bolshoi Theatre. 18:20
Sergey Petrovich!
Comrade Stepanov!
Hello.
Yakov Mikhailovich?
- Yes?
On behalf of our faction we would like to ask
to have the floor for an extraordinary statement.
Alright.
Marya Aleksandrovna, I will stay here.
- Good.
Lenin's still not here?
Not yet.
Well, comrades.
Let's begin.
We've got the quorum.
I ask presidium members
to take the stage.
And delegates to take their seats.
Dzerzhinsky has been arrested by the Left
SR central committee. What do we do? Peters.
Watch Sverdlov.
Comrades!
The Congress presidium just got a note.
The Bolshevik faction
is asking before the work starts
for a small ten minute meeting.
I don't think this should raise any strong objections.
The faction is asking Bolshevik Congress delegates
and the guests of the Bolshevik faction members
to proceed to the opposite side of the street,
to the Second House of Soviets.
In fifteen to twenty minutes
the Congress will reconvene.
Viktor Aleksandrovich!
Always with the surprises, Yakov Mikhailovich.
What to do, Marya Aleksandrovna.
Our entire life consists of suprises, big or small.
Learn what's happening there.
Immediately block all exits and entrances.
Nobody is to be let out until further notice.
Everybody must be at their seats.
Tell our delegates
to gather at Malaya Dmitrovka street.
Nikolay Dmitriyevich!
- Yes?
Wait for me.
Malaya Dmitrovka?
- Malaya Dmitrovka.
Yakov Mikhailovich.
Excuse us.
Vladimir Ilyich
is sending this.
The Left SR faction
is to be arrested.
Already done.
You can't go on the stage.
Why is that?
Orders of comrade Latsis.
This is becoming ridiculous.
What if we want to smoke, not
to mention something else?
What happened?
Smoke here.
Interesting.
What's happening?
- Nobody knows anything.
We have to know.
What's happening, comrades?
- Guards aren't letting anybody out.
Comrades, orders of comrade Latsis!
What orders?
We have orders!
- What is happening there?
Marya Aleksandrovna, I think
we've just been arrested.
In any case they aren't letting us out.
Calm down, comrades!
We have been hypocritically deceived!
And deception has never
been a sign of strength!
I call for you to keep revolutionary calm!
Stay cool, comrades.
Citizens SRs,
you all shall remain here
until further orders from the
Council of People's Commissars.
Popov's troops. 19:40
Marya Aleksandrovna
along with the whole faction
has been arrested by Peters.
Okay, do it. We're waiting.
Bolshoi Theatre
is surrounded.
I barely made it out.
Wait a minute.
- I don't know anything more.
Well then.
At least it's clear now.
There they go, your beloved Bolsheviks.
- Mine?! - Well it's your blunder.
You dreamed of merging the parties with them.
Arresting people's elected delegates! Even
the tsarist government didn't stoop to this.
We must free our comrades with weapons in our arms.
We must do it immediately. And...
Before all.
- Before all:
The telegraph.
The telephone.
Power plants, rail stations, bridges.
Do you want to leave Spiridonova in their hands?
For Mariya Aleksandrovna, I will not only level the Bolshoi,
I'll level half the Kremlin and Lubyanka as well!
Can you give me a small strike force?
I'll take a hundred men and an armored car.
We'll hit them from the metropoly's side and blow all their...
Guard.
- I'm going with you.
And I.
Comrades, but this is...
Fratricide!
- Yes, and what do you suggest?
It's always the same question and the same answer.
"We've got no other choice".
I get Popov with revolutionary winds
in his head, but you, Proshyan?
They are our comrades who made
the revolution happen alongside us.
Split bread and salt.
You.
Will you shoot
at Peters?
Lenin? Sverdlov?
Why are you silent?
"No other choice" you say?
21:10. SRs took the telegraph.
(the rebellion chronicle)
Part of the Moscow garrison switched to the SR side.
They were also joined by...
the VChK cavalry detachment.
Kolchanov's artillery division...
Right now I'm only interested in those who stayed.
Vladimir Ilyich.
All the best have been sent to the frontlines.
Besides, there's Yaroslavl.
We're left with only the Kremlin regiment,
infantry school cadets and the division
of Latvian Riflemen. But they aren't in the city.
Why isn't the Latvian division in Moscow?
Every detachment aside from the Kremlin regiment
are stationed at summer camps.
Besides, today
is Ivan's day.
(Ivan Kupala; Saint John's Eve, summer solstice)
So what?
- It's our main holiday.
And what do the Latvians think?
Are you certain about them?
We have information on the SRs
having done some work there.
But with what results, hard to say.
- Right.
I called for Vatsetis.
He's handling operations with Muralov.
I want to send him to the Latvians.
- Out of the question.
He's a seasoned military man, we
should leave him on operations.
It's better to send...
a good party worker, a Latvian.
We should send Danishevsky.
I'll call for him.
How...
How does Vatsetis evaluate the situation?
Where is he?
He's here, Vladimir Ilyich.
Comrade Vatsetis.
Can we hold out until morning?
The situation is unclear, Vladimir Ilyich.
We're almost out of troops.
Comrade Podvoysky and I, we want
to go survey the city, but we need time.
How much?
A couple hours, Vladimir Ilyich.
- Yes.
We'll give you an answer in two hours.
It's almost 10, and very little has been done so far.
We're constantly losing initiative.
I need you to understand this.
An pass it on to all the comrades.
If we don't take some desperate measures to turn this slop
into something solid,
we'll get toppled.
The situation is out of hand.
Badly.
I will be waiting.
What?
Not answering.
Maybe we should send another telegram?
Ioffe isn't answering because the Germans aren't answering.
Adolf Abramovich Ioffe, RSFSR ambassador in Germany
Vladimir Ilyich, Danishevsky is waiting.
So what, comrade Danishevsky?
I don't have to explain it to you.
The Brest Peace has deprived Latvians of their motherland.
Perfect grounds for SR agitation.
Go now.
And come back no matter what.
We must know if we should be expecting these
regiments or taking other measures.
I'll try, Vladimir Ilyich.
Vladimir Ilyich.
I'm going to Dmitrovka.
Our faction is gathering there.
Mobilize every government member,
central committee members too.
We'll arm the worker detachments and be ready.
Accompanying the district delegates will be...
Smidovich to Sokolniki.
Skrypnik to the Rogozhko-Simonovsky district.
Zinovyev to Gorodskoy, Tsuryupa and Schlichter to Zamoskvorechye.
Schlichter's better for Lefortovo.
Alright.
Teodorovich and Podbelsky to Basmanny,
Kamenev to Trubnaya.
And to Presnya?
Bubnov.
Lenin's at Sovnarkom, Sverdlov's at Congress, Bukharin's at Pravda, Steklov's at Izvestiya,
Sklyansky is at the War Commissariat...
- Let him focus on Yaroslavl.
Completely! Lashevich too.
Alright.
Ioffe's in Berlin, Petrovsky, Artyom and Kollontai are in Ukraine,
Stalin is in Tsaritsyn,
Rykov is in Kazan...
- Send Stalin and Rykov detailed telegrams on everything.
We should send Uritsky and Zaslavsky to Peter.
Saint Petersburg
In case SRs plot something there as well.
Yeah...
The question
of the Latvian division
isn't just military.
It's a political question now.
If the Latvians,
whom SRs promised to return the motherland to,
will stand against the rebels,
it will prove to everyone
that our policy is correct.
But if they don't...
SR troops have surrounded the city center.
Stop there!
Papers.
Surname?
Danishevsky.
The car has been requisitioned for the Left SR party. Come out.
We aren't going anywhere.
Where's your commander?
Yeryokhin!
Yeryokhin, it's for you.
Who might you be?
- Latvian Riflemen.
Let them through.
You may pass, comrades.
Let them through!
We're expecting you, comrades!
Malaya Dmitrovka street, 6.
22:10
Comrades!
Left SR party has mutinied!
Dzerzhinsky has been arrested.
A Congress delegate has been murdered.
Abelman.
The situation is extremely grave.
There has been a proposition
to spread all the members of our faction
around Moscow districts
to assist the local forces.
At stake
is the very existence of the Soviet proletarian power.
The fate of the revolution.
Assigned to the districts:
Basmanny district.
Ananyin.
Gulevsky.
Paul.
Kozlov.
Baranov.
Gorkin.
Melnikov.
Mayorov.
Stepanov.
Krzhanovsky.
Trofimov.
Tumanyan.
Zyuzin.
Pavlov.
Gorlova.
Shurov.
Armand.
Kochetkov.
Smirnov.
Feldman.
Mikharilov.
Tsvetkov.
Vikman.
Zavyalov.
Fazanov.
Ogurchikov.
Titov.
Schlichte.
Rallies have started up in Moscow worker districts.
It has been done dishonorably!
It has been done in the Soviet power name!
It is a betrayal
the likes of which has not been known in history,
Congress delegate Inessa Armand
at least the history of revolution!
It's an act of treachery that could only be done
by Azefs of the revolution!
Yevno Azef, agent provocateur for Okrana in the SR organization
It is a fall that a political party could not ever recover from.
At two Soviet Congresses, the absolute majority
has unequivocally voice their will:
peace and peace only!
And if a Soviet party proclaims the right
Lunacharsky, People's Commissar for Education
at any moment interdict a Soviet decision
Shulgin...
I shall allow myself to note that that party,
in boundaries of the present state,
has no place to exist!
Claiming for themselves a monopoly
on custody of the world revolution,
Left SRs are in fact shooting it in the back.
Vladimir Ilyich was right saying
Frunze, Congress delegate
that we should fight a revolutionary slogan
so they don't say about us later
that a revolutionary slogan
about a revolutionary war
brought the revolution's demise!
Everyone should understand we're not talking about
one ruling party taking the place of another's.
If the Soviet power slips today,
Bubnov, RKP central committee member
tomorrow the counter-revolution will have the power
to crush any revolutionary force like an iron mill
not bothering to tell Bolsheviks from SRs!
At this difficult moment when the fate
of our conquests is being decided,
the Russian Communist Bolshevik party is certain
Karpov, Congress delegate
that you will stand up to defend
these proletarian conquests.
We shall win this July
like we had won in October.
Worker Moscow was raising up.
- To Zamoskvorechye: Ivashov,
Kutuzov,
Buravin,
Malyshev,
Dymnov,
Nazarov,
Ryabin,
Krivosheev,
Kiselev,
Gavrilin,
The Kremlin. 23:30
No.
You need an army to fight an army.
Workers should only fight
as the last-ditch measure.
We wait.
I don't know, Vladimir Ilyich.
We can't put untrained people under fire.
What does Danishevsky say?
Vladimnir Ilyich, Berlin.
Well, the murder of the ambassador
is too good of a trump card.
It would be naive to think
the Germans wouldn't use it.
That means we should expect the worst demands.
Yes indeed, that's what it means.
And what would stop them,
especially in these cicrcumstances?
You think Berlin already knows about the mutiny?
I don't think it, I'm sure of it.
Well then, let's forget about the Left SRs for a minute.
Georgiy Vasilyevich.
Let us consider every possible German demand.
What could be the Germans' reaction tomorrow?
Breaking the Brest treaty,
ordering the army, which is still
quite capable, to march on Moscow.
You want to start with this?
Of course.
And our reparations talks?
Why would the Germans want
to lose such a fortune?
What are you talking
about, Vladimir Ilyich?
The rewards of an offensive like that will
so far exceed your puny reparations
that there can be no two opinions on this.
Ruthless man, Georgiy Vasilyevich.
But how...
War.
So we go with what the SRs proposed?
That's exactly what they want.
Well, maybe that is exactly the historical destiny of the Left SRs.
To become the cherry pit we stumble
over, serving the White Guard's needs.
Alright then.
There's another possibility.
They could demand increased security of the embassy.
They would be welcome.
By admitting to Moscow a batallion, maybe a
regiment of their troops.
Very well could be, there are precedents.
Military presence for protection of their subjects.
Well, Georgiy Vasilyevich!
We won't allow that.
There are limits.
We'll mobilize the entire people.
All adult population...
So war?
We're back to the beginning.
War, war, war...
War is demise.
0:20
SRs took the VChK building and arrested Latsis.
(the rebellion chronicle)
Comrade Podvoysky, what do we do? A roadblock is ahead.
Take the right.
Stop!
Stop I say!
Now go straight ahead!
Stop or I'll shoot!
Stop! Stop!
Go to the Pokrovsky barracks!
Right then.
1st March regiment has also taken the SR's side.
Stop here.
Back up!
Quick! Quick!
We'll try to break through the Kursk station.
Stop!
Stop! Stop!
Popov's detachment. 0:40
How could you go against the Soviet power?
Why against?
We're not against it.
Popov himself said we're fighting for the Soviets.
But with no peace.
So you want to go to war again?
We've got orders.
Whose orders?
Stop chatting. You are in prison.
Felix Edmundovich!
We all respect you.
Our cause is honest and true.
With us the whole Zamoskvorechye,
Pokrovsky barracks, the 1st March regiment.
Muravyev, the eastern front
commander, is on our side.
Stand with us, Felix Edmundovich!
- If I had a revolver right now,
I would put a bullet in your head, you traitor.
Martin Yanovich.
Look at you.
You are a revolutionary.
Real comrade.
A Latvian.
Germans are choking Latvia, killing our comrades,
and you protect Mirbach? Aren't you ashamed?
Oh I'm ashamed that I didn't kill you yesterday!
You contra.
counter-revolutionary
So this is it then.
If we don't get you,
Then you get us!
- Oh we will get you either way.
And why are you quite, Aleksandrovich?
How could you.
I trusted you.
I am a Left SR party
member, Felix Edmundovich.
And I did what the CC of my party decided I should.
Well then.
Seeing you as a disciplined party member,
I'm shaking your hand.
But as my VChK deputy,
I will get you a fire squad.
1:10
SRs took the power station.
(the rebellion chronicle)
Right now, the SRs have more than two thousand
bayonets.
Artillery,
over sixty machine guns
and several armored cars.
I left Vatsetis
at Muralov's headquarters.
I have matches.
They have the power station.
Yes, Tsygankov's detachment
has been already sent there.
We have reinforced what little troops
we had with Congress delegates.
Distributed all the party cadres.
Sent comrades out to the rail stations,
to the barracks, to separate batallions.
But all that is not nearly enough.
Not nearly enough, Vladimir Ilyich.
The SRs took the Chistye Prudy district,
took Vsesvyatskoye, took the entire Zamoskvorechye.
They drove us back over the Yauza
and are pulling their forces toward the
center now.
I barely managed to break through to you.
My impression is they are preparing to storm the Kremlin.
Vladimir Ilyich, Latsis has been arrested.
The VChK building is overtaken by the SRs.
Kuznetsov came from there.
Right.
Vladimir Ilyich.
If we hear nothing from Danishevsky in an hour,
we should arm the worker
detachments. There's no other way.
I'll go brief the comrades on the situation,
and we will think over the
defense measures for the Kremlin.
Call Peters.
He's now appointed the VChK chairman.
And call for Gorbunov, please.
Comrade Gorbunov.
Prepare everything necessary to move the government
to the Khodynka artillery barracks.
You understand me?
Popov's detachment 1:50
- The morning papers should be printed
announcing the first session of the new government.
And this session must be held in the Kremlin.
The Kremlin will be taken by morning.
The Kremlin must be taken by night.
Now.
Immediately.
- No question.
A night storm could cost us half the detachment.
But by morning my hands will be untied,
and I will be able to use artillery.
Listen, two hours won't decide anything.
Two hours can decide it all. Don't you understand
what is happening in the city? Tell him.
In every district,
the Bolsheviks are organizing worker detachments.
They are for now poorly armed.
But by the morning they would be a serious force.
Well that makes it worse!
Comrades, we can't sacrifice the detachment!
Alright, it's decided.
At 4:30 we start the shelling
and immediately storm in. By 5 it will all be over.
It's decided.
The main thing is to win.
Then it all will settle down.
Don't know who will win but I'm
afraid the revolution will be the loser.
Comrade Proshyan,
you should write a proclamation for the workers.
I will, I will.
Bolshoi Theatre. 2:10
Where's Turov?
Turov's!
We can't wait anymore, we must act.
We are about four hundred strong, many are armed.
The guard is no more than a hundred.
Break people into groups, disseminate orders. The signal is Varshavyanka*.
Varshavyanka - Polish/Russian revolutionary song
2:30.
The SRs have taken the phone station and disconnected the Kremlin.
(the rebellion chronicle)
The Kremlin. 3:10
What if we don't say anything?
You?
I'm a member of VTsIK*.
VTsIK (ВЦИК) - All-Russian Central Executive Committee
Only the Congress can deprive me of authority.
I need to speak with Vladimir Ilyich.
Wait here.
Vladimir Ilyich.
Kolegayev is here to see you.
Who now?
Yes, yes.
Kolegayev Andrey Lukyanovich.
There it is then.
An ultimatum.
Well then.
Ultimatum it is.
Invite him in.
I do understand the sheer
absurdity of my appearance here.
But the revolution's fate is at stake.
We are listening.
Vladimir Ilyich, the revolution
is suffering a great tragedy.
We should stop. We are murdering the revolution.
You tell this to us?
I said the same over there.
We should find common ground. We must talk it through.
I don't understand you.
What is this?
A proposal of your party?
Vladimir Ilyich, I'm here as a person who
holds our common cause interests most dear.
Excuse me, but we don't have time
for personal matters right now.
Vladimir Ilyich, you don't
have the right to say so.
We must stand above our parties' qualms.
The entire Russia's fate
may well depend on it.
Understand, when Robespierre and Danton
couldn't strike a deal, only Napoleon won.
What could be more terrible than a
schism among the revolutionaries?
A fraudulent unity.
There can be no unity with people
who could at any moment put the
country at the brink of catastrophe,
none!
Tell your friends, comrade Kolegayev, that
since yesterday, July the 6th, Russia
has got one party fewer.
I quit that party.
Maybe they just mistreated you?
Vladimir Ilyich.
When I worked under you
as a government member,
you had enough opportunity to see who I am.
You all fled the government.
You are a government member who fled.
To say it plainly,
a deserter.
You all are deserters
who got scared of
responsibility.
Vladimir Ilyich, we didn't want
to be responsible for your policy
because we didn't agree with it.
But it was perfectly possible for you
to stay in opposition and critique us.
You had organization, newspapers, money.
You had everything
an opposition party could dream of.
And you?
Instead of a loyal
opposition, conspirators.
Pawns in White Guard's hands.
Theirs and others'.
- Well, you are right about that.
Of course.
Suicides.
A central committee of suicides.
And I am sure that this whole adventure
will push away not only most
of your workers and peasants,
but many of the intelligentsiya too.
And with these same people we'll form a new party.
- What party?
- Revolutionary communist party.
- And you will insist again
that no amount of human
sacrifice however great it is
must stop us on our way
to the world revolution?
Great goals, Vladimir Ilyich,
can't be reached without great sacrifice.
I know of only one great goal.
Human happiness.
And not of some
abstract humans,
but those same humans you intend
to sacrifice.
This is not the time for political debate!
And even worse of a time
for political compromise.
I am very sorry, Vladimir Ilyich, that we
can not understand each other in such a fatal way.
Goodbye.
Vladimir Ilyich, sorry, have you read it?
Yes.
Almost.
There are some margin notes.
What's in the city?
An SR detachment arrived
to the Nikolaevsky station.
The backup.
Probably.
The Basmanny district worker
militia was able to disarm them.
- How many were there?
- About a hundred.
Increased activity of the SRs in Bolshoi Theatre.
Peters' report.
Chewing us out?
Singing songs.
Each more revolutionary than the last.
Are they armed?
They could be.
To Peters.
Bolshoi Theatre
Citizens SRs,
The All-Russian Extraordinary Commission
invites you all to give up your weapons.
Don't do it comrades!
This is an outrage!
We won't give up our arms!
To the odious and disgraceful demand
to give up or weapons
we answer with a refusal!
Those detained in possession
of arms in an hour
will be judged with all the
severity of revolutionary law.
Tell Lenin and Sverdlov
we don't want to take part in this comedy.
We don't recognize your
judgement and never will!
Please give up your weapons.
Please.
Please follow the example
of citizen Spiridonova.
It's our fire!
Keep your heads up comrades!
Long live the revolution!
The Kremlin. 4:35
They're starting with cannons...
Well, well.
Ivan Vasilyevich, please
check with the guardposts.
They're starting.
Looks like it.
Vladimir Ilyich!
The Latvian division is entering the city.
At 5:10 the Latvian Riflemen division entered
Moscow from Khodynka side.
(the rebellion chronicle)
The Kremlin. 5:40
These troops should be placed around the Cathedral of Christ the Saviour
and Strastnaya Square.
Your regiment stays in reserves.
Move it
to Arbat, here.
We must remember
that the opposing force
is still largely surpassing our own.
The main strike should occur at the A ring.
Your regiments should march there.
And from here, from the Pokrovsky Gate.
Also from there
we will start shelling
of the Tryohsvyatitelsky alley.
- The artillery wouldn't pass from the Pokrovka.
It's all dug up.
I know.
The guns will have to be pulled by hand.
At the time of the storm
the guns will open on the SR headquarters.
We'll hold off with the artillery.
We should offer them a chance to surrender.
Give them twenty minutes to think it over.
Alright.
We will try it.
Your batallion,
Dudin's regiment
and the artillery cadets
should take all the bridges
and checkpoints.
In no circumstances the SR troops
stationed in the Pokrovsky barracks
should be allowed to join the main forces.
Is this clear, comrades?
Any questions?
- I need machine guns.
- How many?
- Two or three.
Can we get some, comrade Vatsetis?
I must think about it.
Vladimir Ilyich,
they are shelling the Kremlin.
I can see it.
Well then.
They've made their choice.
6:10
Where to, Vladimir Ilyich?
Sokolniki.
We won't be back in an hour,
and they are still shooting there.
- Sokolniki.
The All-Russian Congress of Soviets
reconvenes.
July 9th 1918.
The 5th All-Russian Congress of Soviets
reconvened.